Hi everybody, I'm John Kuryaku and this
is Deep Focus. Two days ago on Friday,
June 13th, Israel attacked Iran in a
preemptive strike to try to destroy the
Iranian nuclear weapons program. For
what that's worth, the Iranians have
said repeatedly over the course of
decades that they don't have a nuclear
weapons program.
It's a long story, but the Iranians have
been enriching uranium first to 30%
enrichment, then to 67% enrichment. 95%
is considered to be weapons grade. And
it's not hard to get from 67% to 95%.
In the meantime, over the past several
months, the Trump administration has
been engaged in direct talks with the
Iranians to try to get this whole
situation under control whereby the
Iranians would be allowed presumably to
enrich uranium. But what the Trump
administration wants is that the uranium
would then be stored somewhere in an
Arab country on the Arabian Peninsula,
probably Abu Dhabi or Dubai in the
United Arab Emirates.
That was all unacceptable to the Israeli
government of Benjamin Netanyahu. And
the attacks began late Friday night.
Well, so far there are 78 Iranians dead,
more than 320 wounded uh versus three
Israelis killed and and two dozen
wounded. But the Israelis did something
that was uh that was long in the
planning. They tried to take out and
they almost succeeded in taking out the
entire Iranian military leadership. They
killed the military chief of staff. They
killed the head of the uh Revolutionary
Guard Corps, which is the the preeminent
uh armed body in Iran. Uh they killed
the head of the nuclear program. They
killed the country's top scientist. And
they did it primarily from inside Iran.
We learned yesterday that that Iranians
reported that these men before they were
killed had notes slipped under their
apartment doors saying that they were
going to be killed. They had calls made
to their cell phones and in some cases
calls to their wives cell phones saying,
"Time is short. You're going to die."
And then the Israelis did exactly that.
And what the Israelis didn't expect was
for the Iranians to respond with the
ferocity that they have. The Iranians
have launched at least two waves of
drones and ballistic missiles so far,
and they've hit things like the um IDF
in Israel, the Israel Defense Force, the
Defense Ministry. Uh they've destroyed a
uh a surfaceto-air missile battery uh in
Tel Aviv. We heard today that
the Israeli government has reached out
to the Iranian government through third
countries asking them to please stop
attacking.
That's rich. But that's what they're
doing. They thought they could take out
the nuclear program in one strike. It
didn't work. The Israelis bombed Natans,
which is the biggest Iranian nuclear
facility. The IAEA, the International
Atomic Energy Agency, reports that there
is a nuclear leak at Natans, but it's
not destroyed.
So now we have to wait and see. The
Russians have said that Iran is under
the protection of the Russian nuclear
umbrella. The Israelis don't dare use
nuclear weapons against the Iranians
because that risks the Russians using
nuclear weapons against them.
In the meantime, the Trump
administration is applauding the Israeli
action. So, we'll see where it goes. In
the meantime, it looks like war. Thanks
for joining me. Do me a favor. Please
hit the subscribe and like button. It
really means a lot to me. and we'll see
you very soon on Deep Focus.